{"tossups": [{"question": "This leader o\u21b5ered to take in 100,000 Jewish refugees at the Evian Conference, although only 800 Jews were settled in the town of Sosua. This leader was killed in an ambush of his blue Chevrolet while travelling towards San Cristobal. The International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women is on the anniversary of the assassination of the Mirabal sisters, who opposed this leader. Johnny Abbes Garcia led this leader\u2019s secret police force, known as the SIM. This leader ordered killings of thousands of Haitians in the Parsley Massacre. For the point, name this longtime dictator of the Dominican Republic.", "answer": "Rafael<b> Trujillo</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During this event, the 28th Mountain Division attempted to break out to the city of Tuzla but were ambushed at Kamenica Hill. The Dutchbat were forced to retreat by the VRS prior to this event. The Drina Valley surrounding this event\u2019s location was mistakenly declared a \u201csafe area.\u201d Forces under Ratko Mladi\u00b4c [m\u2019lah-ditch] were responsible for this event, which Kofi Annan labeled as the worst mass murder in Europe since World War II. For the point, name this 1995 massacre of Muslim Bosniaks in a namesake town.", "answer": "<b> Srebrenica</b> [s\u2019reh-breh-neet-zah] massacre (or genocide, etc.)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A film executive who would go on to become a mayor in Florida was listed at the beginning of this document. Charles Colson authored this document, which he compiled while serving as a \u201chatchet man.\u201dDaniel Schorr read this document on public television, expressing surprise at finding his own name on it. John Dean revealed the existence of this document, whose subjects were to be targeted with IRS tax audits and restrictions on government contracts. A set of hearings in 1973 brought to light, for the point, what infamous list that included actor Paul Newman and 19 other political opponents of a US president?", "answer": "Richard M(ilhous)<b> Nixon</b>\u2019s<b> list</b> of<b> enemies</b> (or the<b> Political Enemies Project</b>; accept descriptive equivalents; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "While fighting at the First Battle of Ypres [eep], this man took a sniper\u2019s bullet through the lung, taking him out of World War I for 3 years. After World War II, this man served as the first Deputy Supreme Allied Commander of Europe. This man critically chose to have eight, rather than three, divisions make up the landing force on D-Day. This man was described as a \u201ctired little fart\u201d by George Patton, who this man helped to take Sicily. This leader of the Eighth Army won the Second Battle of El Alamein during the North African Campaign. For the point, name this British general.", "answer": "Bernard<b> Montgomery</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this modern-day country, a man claimed to have received a vision from a \u201cMaid of Heaven\u201d while imprisoned in the Siyah-Chal [SEE-yah chahl]. As Chancellor, Amir Kabir was notorious for suppressing minority religions in this country, where Subh-i-Azal led a splinter religious faction claiming to be the true followers of the B\u00b4ab [bob], who initially claimed to be Mahdi. Followers of a religion founded in this country built the Universal House of Justice in Haifa, Israel. For the point, name this country where the Baha\u2019i Faith was founded and has been persecuted by Ayatollah Khamenei.", "answer": "<b> Iran</b> (or<b> Persia</b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "A member of the Little Circle named John Edward Taylor founded this newspaper in 1821. This paper claimed that \u201cneither side can escape condemnation\u201d for a 1972 incident at Bogside. This newspaper published a scoop on a scandal in which a murdered 11-year old named Milly Dowler and victims of a 2005 metro bombing had their phones hacked by<em> News of the World</em>, which led to Rupert Murdoch\u2019s resignation. Edward Snowden initially leaked his information to, for the point, what left-leaning British daily newspaper?", "answer": "The<b> Guardian</b> (accept the Manchester<b> Guardian</b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "One of these objects was used to kill commander Arthur Aston in the siege of Drogheda [drau-duh]. A general known as \u201cOld Silver Nails\u201d began to use one of these objects after a failed raid on Saint Martin. One of these objects is on display in Springfield, Illinois, having been captured by the 4th Illinois Infantry during the Mexican-American War; that object was originally used after its owner was struck by a cannonball during the Pastry War. The governor of New Amsterdam, Peter Stuyvesant, used, for the point, what type of prosthesis used by Santa Anna?", "answer": "prosthetic<b> leg</b> (accept artificial<b> leg</b> or other equivalents; accept Operation Wooden<b> Leg</b>; accept wooden<b> leg</b>; accept cork<b> leg</b> after \u201cSpringfield\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This leader once received a gift of 31 live myrrh trees after establishing trading relations with the Land of Punt. As a sign of recovery from the Hyksos occupation, this leader embarked on building projects like the Red Chapel at Karnak and the Unfinished Obelisk in Aswan. This pharaoh was interred in the first Valley of the Kings tomb built, KV20, although many monuments dedicated to this pharaoh were later e\u21b5aced by Thutmose III, her son and co-regent. For the point, name this prominent female Egyptian pharaoh of the 18th Dynasty.", "answer": "<b> Hatshepsut</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "The Flechas were a unit of natives that helped this country police its colonies. A fugitive member of the OAS founded Aginter Press in this country while serving as a cover for an anti-communist mercenary force. Immigrants who arrived in this country after the end of its colonial empire were known as the<em> retornados</em>. Antonio Salazar established the Estado Novo regime in, for the point, what country where the Carnation Revolution took place in Lisbon?", "answer": "<b> Portugal</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Immigrants from the Panyu district carried this language to the United States. Yuan Chonghuan\u2019s battle cry was used in protests over this language in 2010. This is the prestige dialect of the Yue [yu] language group, which also includes such languages as Toishanese. According to legend, this language almost became the national language after the 1911 Xinhai [shin-hai] Revolution. The primary language in Guangdong Province is, for the point, what southern Chinese dialect, spoken in Guangzhou and Hong Kong, that is mutually unintelligible to Mandarin?", "answer": "<b> Cantonese</b> (prompt on Chinese before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This speech quotes Speaker John Carlisle on the \u201cstruggle between the idle holders of idle capital and the struggling masses who produce the wealth.\u201d This speech, which compares Cicero\u2019s exposure of the Cataline plot to Andrew Jackson\u2019s anti-bank policy, ended with its speaker holding his arms outstretched. This speech urged the masses not to \u201cpress down upon the brow of labor this crown of thorns\u201d in a condemnation of the gold standard. For the point, name this speech given at the 1896 Democratic National Convention by William Jennings Bryan.", "answer": "<b> Cross of Gold</b> speech (prompt on descriptions of William Jennings Bryan\u2019s 1896 Democratic National Convention speech before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Melting Arctic ice now allows relatively easy shipping through, for the point, what long-sought sea route through North America?", "answer": "<b> Northwest Passage</b> (prompt on North America or descriptions of the New World during the first sentence)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The 2013 film<em> The Missing Picture</em> depicts the rule of this group in the form of clay animation. In 1997, Nate Thayer was able to conduct an interview with this group\u2019s leader a year before he died. This group was responsible for killing around 40 percent of the Cham population, and it operated a prison that is now the Tuol Sleng Genocide Museum. This group was ousted from power after a 1979 invasion from neighboring Vietnam. For the point, name this communist group that was responsible for the killing fields in Cambodia under Pol Pot.", "answer": "<b> Khmer Rouge</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In this state\u2019s capital, William West led a march with members of the Country Party in an e\u21b5ort to lobby for the Bill of Rights. The first major action of the Comte d\u2019Estaing\u2019s fleet in the Revolutionary War was at an abortive siege in this state. This was the home state of colonial commander Nathaniel Greene. John Brown and Abraham Whipple led the burning of a British customs enforcement schooner in this state in the Gaspee A\u21b5air. For the point, name this state where British forces held o\u21b5a siege of Newport.", "answer": "<b> Rhode Island</b> and Providence Plantations", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The \u201cTraitorous Eight\u201d left a lab dedicated to this technology to start a company of their own with the help of Sherman Fairchild; the lab they left was run by William Shockley, who shared the 1956 Nobel Prize in Physics with Walter Brattain and John Bardeen for discovering these devices. These devices are often made using germanium or silicon, which gives Silicon Valley its name due to their crucial presence in computers. For the point, name this type of material that has conductivity between that of insulators and conductors.", "answer": "<b> semiconductor</b>s (accept<b> transistor</b> before \u201cdiscovering\u201d is read, and anti-prompt on transistor by asking \u201ccan you be less specific?\u201d after)", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "A character in this work repeatedly paints a pond in his backyard to get over the death of his daughter, Marigold. The main character of this work learns of her father\u2019s death while on a Kenyan safari. In this work, Vanessa Kirby portrays a woman who falls in love with a divorced air force group leader, Peter Townshend. The first episode of this series focuses on a lavish wedding in which Philip, Duke of Edinburgh marries into the royal family. For the point, name this Netflix series about the life of Queen Elizabeth II.", "answer": "The<b> Crown</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "For the point, name this country that employed the Jericho missile during the Yom Kippur War.", "answer": "<b> Israel</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Nicetas Chroniates made note of this woman\u2019s eptithet, \u201cgolden foot.\u201d One of this woman\u2019s husbands considered divorcing her for the \u201cRose of Unchastity.\u201d The Rolls of Oleron were promoted by this ruler as maritime law. This woman\u2019s husband lost the Battle of Mount Cadmus in the Second Crusade. Andreas Cappellanus described this woman, Ermengande of Narbonne, and Isabelle of Flanders as operating a Court of Love in Poitiers. John I and Richard I of England were children of, for the point, what queen who married Louis VII and Henry II of England?", "answer": "<b> Eleanor of Aquitaine</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A protest by workers who produced this good was led by Abbas Tyabji [t\u2019yahb-jee]. A barrier called the Great Hedge was erected to prevent the smuggling of this good, which was produced extensively in Dharasana. The Second Round Table Conference arose after a protest revolving around this good that ended after negotiations with Lord Irwin. Vedaranyam was the site of a protest against the taxation of, for the point, what good whose British taxation was protested by a march to Dandi led by Mahatma Gandhi, who broke the law by reclaiming this good from seawater?", "answer": "<b> salt</b> (accept<b> Salt</b> March or<b> Salt</b> Satyagraha)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The perpetrator of this action defended himself in the open letter \u201cTo the Inhabitants of America.\u201dAfter this plot was exposed, the perpetrator fled to New York City on board the<em> Vulture</em>, where he was joined by his wife, Peggy Shippen. Henry Clinton agreed to pay 20,000 pounds to the perpetrator of this plot, which was exposed when John Andre was captured in Tarrytown. The British would have gained control over the Hudson River in, for the point, what failed act of treason during the Revolutionary War?", "answer": "Benedict<b> Arnold</b>\u2019s surrender of<b> West Point</b> to the British (accept Benedict<b> Arnold</b>\u2019s <b>defection</b> to the British or equivalents; prompt on partial answers, like \u201cBenedict Arnold\u2019s plot\u201d or \u201cthe surrender of West Point\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Members of this organization lived in a safe house in Big Spring Park in Pennsylvania, from where they planned an attack on the Hungry Horse and Flathead Dams in Montana. Markus Hess was employed in the 1980s as a hacker by this organization, which created a poisoned jewel box in an attempt to kill Josip Tito. The GRU was the military counterpart to this organization, which saw many of its agents compromised during the Red Scare. The NKVD was a predecessor of, for the point, what Soviet security agency?", "answer": "<b> KGB</b> (or the<b> Komitet gosudarstvennoy bezopasnosti</b>; accept<b> Committee for State Security</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One of these objects brought to the White House by Andrew Jackson in memory of Rachel Donelson is currently in poor condition. Nathaniel Coffin Jr. destroyed one of these objects in Boston that was a gathering place for Stamp Act protests. Connecticut\u2019s Royal Charter of 1662 was hidden from Edmund Andros inside one of these objects. A Parson Weems biography relates how a six year old boy destroyed one of these objects. For the point, name these plants, one of which a young George Washington supposedly chopped down.", "answer": "<b> tree</b>s (accept<b> magnolia</b>,<b> oak</b>, or<b> cherry</b> trees; prompt on plant before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A seated depiction of this man uses a background of leaves with chrysanthemums, jasmine and blue lilies; Kehinde Wiley, the artist of that portrait of this man for the National Portrait Gallery, intended for those flowers to represent this man\u2019s heritage. Graphic designer Shepard Fairey used shades of blue and red to show this leader with the word \u201cHOPE\u201d in blue letters during this leader\u2019s 2008 campaign. For the point, name this 44th President of the United States.", "answer": "Barack<b> Obama</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A Francis Poulenc opera is based on the executions of 16 women who served this organization in Compi`egne. The assignat was backed by the lands of this organization, which were broken up and sold in large plots. Napoleon restored the standing of this organization with the Concordat of 1801. Members of this organization who refused to follow a certain law were termed \u201crefractory;\u201dthose members rejected the Civil Constitution of the Clergy. For the point, name this religious organization whose lands were confiscated during the French Revolution.", "answer": "Roman<b> Catholic</b> Church", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}